Guide to the George F. Johnston Company Records WA MSS S-2606
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George F. Johnston Company records
1901-1954
1901-1933
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George F. Johnston Company
WA MSS S-2606
976
36.07 Linear Feet (38 boxes)
The collection consists of records documenting the day-to-day administration and operation of the George F. Johnston Company of Etiwanda, California. The records date from 1901 to 1954, with the bulk dating from 1901 to 1933, and relate to the company's production, sale, and distribution of grapes, its finances, and its labor force, which was primarily Japanese American. Included are correspondence, invoices, statements, sales and expense receipts, shipping logs and manifests, claims records, ledgers, daily time reports and time books, bank documents, and related material. The collection provides documentation of the fruit trade and grape industry in California in the first half of the twentieth century, and sheds light on the work and experiences of fruit growers, viticulturists (grape growers), agricultural laborers, and vineyard laborers (grape pickers) in California during the same period.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the William Robertson Coe Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
George F. Johnston Company
The George F. Johnston Company was a grape growing and distributing company that operated in Etiwanda, California during the first half of the twentieth century--from circa 1905 to 1934 or later--and which supplied table grapes to many parts of the United States. The company was run by George F. Johnston. His sons, J. Spencer Johnston and Philip Johnston, also appear to have played a role in the company.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of records documenting the day-to-day administration and operation of the George F. Johnston Company of Etiwanda, California. The records date from 1901 to 1954, with the bulk dating from 1901 to 1933, and relate to the company's production, sale, and distribution of grapes, its finances, and its labor force, which was primarily Japanese American. Included are correspondence, invoices, statements, sales and expense receipts, shipping logs and manifests, claims records, ledgers, daily time reports and time books, bank documents, and related material.
The collection provides documentation of the fruit trade and grape industry in California in the first half of the twentieth century, and sheds light on the work and experiences of fruit growers, viticulturists (grape growers), agricultural laborers, and vineyard laborers (grape pickers) in California during the same period.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: I. Alphabetical Files, 1912-1933. II. Other General Business Records, 1901-1954. III. Other Sales and Expense Records, 1911-1926. IV. Labor Records, 1915-1933. V. Bank Records, 1911-1950.
This organization represents an order imposed by library staff and is not meant to reflect how the records were organized by the company, but rather to provide access to material which was received by the library in a highly disorganized state. Records that lent themselves to alphabetical arrangement (ie. that could be attributed to a particular entity) were sorted into files by name. The decision to arrange this material alphabetically was based on the fact that small alphabetical groupings were found which seemed to suggest some level of alphabetical organization on the part of the creator. Other more format- or function-based records were organized into series by type.
Researchers should note that material in each series will often overlap with material found in other series, particularly amongst I. Alphabetical Files, II. Other General Business Records, and III. Other Sales and Expense Records. In order to locate all relevant or related material, researchers will likely need to consult each series.
Agricultural laborers -- California; Agriculture -- California -- San Bernardino County; Fruit growers -- California; Fruit trade -- California; Grape industry -- California; Japanese Americans -- California; Vineyard laborers; Viticulturists; Etiwanda (Rancho Cucamonga, Calif.); Account books; Logs (records); Sales records; Shipping records; Time books; Time sheets; Johnston, George F.; Johnston, J. Spencer; Johnston, Philip, Etiwanda (Calif.); George F. Johnston Company
- Alphabetical Files, 1912-1933; 1; 325452; 11.21 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of material attributable to a particular entity, including produce, distribution, shipping, and supply companies with which the George F. Johnston Company did business and individuals who either worked for or did business with the company. Material includes correspondence, statements, invoices, receipts, manifests, shipping receipts, and other material relating to the administration and operation of the company and the sale and shipping of grapes.
  Arrangement
  Arranged into two subseries: Name Files and General Letter Files.
  Related Archival Materials note
  Related material can found in and.
  - Name Files, 325459
    This subseries consists of material relating to particular companies and of sufficient quantity to warrant being arranged into files or file groupings by the name of the company.
    Files are arranged alphabetically. Material within files has not been arranged in any particular order.
    - Arenz Commission Company, 1913; 325485 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Associated Fruit Co., 1924-1926; 325484 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - California Pine Box Distributors (formerly California Pine Box & Lumber Co.), 1912-1933; 325483 (Box 1, Folder 3-15)
    - Consolidated Produce Co., 1932-1933; 325482 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Crombie & Company, 1927-1928; 325481 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
    - Dennis, Kimball & Pope, Inc., 325476
      - 1914-1918, 325480 (Box 2, Folder 20-38)
      - 1918-1922, 325479 (Box 3, Folder 39-56)
      - 1922-1924, 325478 (Box 4, Folder 57-75)
      - 1925-1926, 325477 (Box 5, Folder 76-89)
    - Descalzi Fruit Company, 1913; 325475 (Box 5, Folder 90)
    - Desel-Boettcher Company, 1916-1933; 325474 (Box 5, Folder 91-97)
    - George A. Scott, 1913; 325473 (Box 5, Folder 98)
    - Hancock Brothers Fruit Company, 1915-1918; 325472 (Box 5, Folder 99-100)
    - Harkrider-Keith-Cooke Company, 1913-1914; 325471 (Box 6, Folder 101-102)
    - James F. Fanning Fruit Company, 1913; 325470 (Box 6, Folder 103)
    - John B. Cancelmo Fancy Fruits, 1913; 325469 (Box 6, Folder 104)
    - John Meyer, Inc., 1913-1932; 325468 (Box 6, Folder 105-111)
    - Kimball Fruit Company, 1927-1929; 325467 (Box 6, Folder 112-114)
    - Klein Simpson Fruit Company, 1928; 325466 (Box 6, Folder 115-116)
    - P. L. Cuccia Fruit Company, 1914-1923; 325465 (Box 6, Folder 117)
    - Pruitt Commission Company, 1912-1933; 325464 (Box 6, Folder 118-121)
    - Sgobel & Day, Inc., 1932; 325463 (Box 6, Folder 122-126)
    - Sgobel & Day, Inc., 1932-1933; 325462 (Box 7, Folder 127-136)
    - Sun Maid Raisin Growers (formerly California Associated Raisin Company), 1913-1934; 325461 (Box 7, Folder 137-141)
    - V. T. Monteleone, 1922-1925; 325460 (Box 7, Folder 142-143)
  - General Letter Files, 325453
    This subseries consists of material relating to particular companies and individuals arranged into general files by first letter of the company name or the individual's surname. In certain instances, Johnston would begin conducting correspondence with a company and would later carry on correspondence with an individual from the company. Researchers will likely need to look under both company and individual name to locate all related material.
    - A - C, 1912-1933; 325458 (Box 8, Folder 144-163)
    - D - H, 1913-1932; 325457 (Box 9, Folder 164-185)
    - I - P, 1914-1933; 325456 (Box 10, Folder 186-209)
    - P - S, 1914-1932; 325455 (Box 11, Folder 210-227)
    - T - Z, Unidentified, 1916-1925; 325454 (Box 12, Folder 228-241)
- Other General Business Records, 1901-1954; 2; 325385; 4.83 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
  This series consists of material relating in general to the administration and operation of the George F. Johnston Company. Found here are shipping records including shipping logs and claims records; account records including ledgers; tax records; foreman reports; notebooks; and correspondence. Other materials, which document aspects of the grape industry in general, are a fruit and produce code book dating from 1918 and an undated photograph of Japanese laborers.
  Files are largely arranged in chronological order.
  Related material can be found in and.
  - Land Title, 1901; 325451 (Box 13, Folder 242)
  - Ledgers, 1901-1927; 325450 (Box 13, Folder 243-248)
    See also,, and
  - Shipments Sent and Received, Assets and Liabilities Season 1912, 1905; 325449 (Box 13, Folder 249)
  - Grape Shipments by Wells Fargo & Co. Express, 1908-1909; 325448 (Box 13, Folder 250)
  - Car Record, 1911; 325447 (Box 13, Folder 251)
  - Shipping Claims, 1911; 325446 (Box 14, Folder 252)
  - Grape Accounts, P. L. Cuccia, 1911; 325445 (Box 14, Folder 253)
  - Income Taxes, 1914-1938; 325444 (Box 14, Folder 254-257)
  - County Taxes, 1914-1927; 325443 (Box 14, Folder 258-260)
  - Notebook, 1915, undated; 325442 (Box 14, Folder 261)
  - Shipping and Related Material, 1916; 325441 (Box 15, Folder 262-263)
  - Correspondence, 1916; 325440 (Box 15, Folder 264)
  - J. C. Jones, 1916-1918; 325439 (Box 15, Folder 265)
  - Miscellaneous, 1916-1922; 325438 (Box 15, Folder 266-267)
  - Notebook, 1918; 325437 (Box 15, Folder 268)
  - Fruit and Produce Code Book, 1918; 325436 (Box 15, Folder 269)
  - 1918 Season, 325435 (Box 15, Folder 270)
  - Phillip W. Brooks, 1918-1921; 325434 (Box 15, Folder 271)
  - Notebook, 1919-1921; 325433 (Box 15, Folder 272)
  - Correspondence with J. Spencer Johnston, 1920-1925; 325432 (Box 15, Folder 273)
  - Telegrams to Mrs. George F. Johnston, 1920-1925; 325431 (Box 15, Folder 274)
  - New Purchase Journal, 1920-1927; 325430 (Box 15, Folder 275)
  - Pacific Fruit Express Co., 1921; 325429 (Box 15, Folder 276-277)
  - Miscellaneous, 1923-1924; 325428 (Box 15, Folder 278-281)
  - Fire Insurance Policy, circa 1924; 325427 (Box 15, Folder 282)
  - Railroad Claims, 1924; 325426 (Box 15, Folder 283)
  - Relating to Drainage Canal through New Purchase, 1924; 325425 (Box 15, Folder 284)
  - Relating to 1924 Grape Crop, 325424 (Box 15, Folder 285)
  - Shipping Log, 1925; 325423
  - Printed Material, 1925-1926; 325422 (Box 15, Folder 286)
  - Claims Records, 1926-1933; 325421 (Box 16, Folder 287)
  - Correspondence, 1927; 325420 (Box 16, Folder 288)
  - California Vinyardist Association, 1927-1928; 325419 (Box 16, Folder 289)
  - Foreman Reports, etc., 1927-1928; 325418 (Box 16, Folder 290)
  - Schmidt Lithograph Co., 1928; 325417 (Box 16, Folder 291)
  - "Misc File", 1928; 325416 (Box 16, Folder 292)
  - "Phoenix, Ariz. - John T. Barker Produce Co.", 1928; 325415 (Box 16, Folder 293)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930-1933; 325414 (Box 16, Folder 294)
  - State Compensation Insurance Fund, 1931-1933; 325413 (Box 16, Folder 295)
  - "Cal. Grape Control - Legal Descriptions of Vineyards and Remittance Records", 1931; 325412 (Box 16, Folder 296)
  - "Oakland Fruit and Prod. - Rickett Prod. Co.", 1932; 325411 (Box 16, Folder 297)
  - Claims, 1932; 325410 (Box 16, Folder 298)
  - Rootings, 1932; 325409 (Box 16, Folder 299)
  - Foreman Reports, etc., 1932-1933; 325408 (Box 16, Folder 300-301)
  - California Vinyardists Association, 1932-1933; 325407 (Box 16, Folder 302)
  - Printed Material, 1932; 325406 (Box 16, Folder 303)
  - "L.C.L.", 1933; 325405 (Box 16, Folder 304)
  - Grape Contract / Certificates of Weight and Measure, 1933; 325404 (Box 16, Folder 305)
  - Shipments Etiwanda, 1933; 325403 (Box 16, Folder 306-307)
  - Shipments Mecca, 1933; 325402 (Box 16, Folder 308-309)
  - "Personal and Important Letters", 1933; 325401 (Box 16, Folder 310)
  - Federal State Marketing Service, Grape Report No. 86, 1933; 325400 (Box 16, Folder 311)
  - "Net and Ribbons", 1933; 325399 (Box 16, Folder 312)
  - Schmidt Lithograph Co., 1933; 325398 (Box 16, Folder 313)
  - Shipping Claims, 1933-1934; 325397 (Box 16, Folder 314)
  - Account Book, 1944-1954; 325396 (Box 16, Folder 315)
  - Photographs of Japanese Laborers, undated; 325395 (Box 16, Folder 316)
  - Forms (mostly blank), 325387
    - Confirmation Sheet, undated; 325394 (Box 16, Folder 317)
    - Daily Insurance Report, 1917, undated; 325393 (Box 16, Folder 318-319)
    - Detailed Weight Manifest, undated; 325392 (Box 17, Folder 320)
    - Stemmer Report, undated; 325391 (Box 17, Folder 321)
    - Transfer Report, undated; 325390 (Box 17, Folder 322)
    - Public Weighmaster's Certificate of Weight and Measure, undated; 325389 (Box 17, Folder 323-325)
    - Car Manifest, undated; 325388
  - Company Stamps, undated; 325386 (Box 18)
- Other Sales and Expense Records, 1911-1926; 3; 325368; 2.42 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
  This series consists of receipts, statements, and other material relating to grape sales and operation expenses of the George F. Johnston Company.
  Files are arranged by type in chronological order.
  - Sales Records, 325373
    - Grape Receipts, 1911-1912; 325384 (Box 19, Folder 326-333)
    - Sales Agreements (unsigned copies), 1912; 325383 (Box 19, Folder 334)
    - Statement of Grapes, 1913; 325382 (Box 19, Folder 335)
    - Grape Contract and Receipts, 1920; 325381 (Box 19, Folder 336)
    - Grape Receipts, 1921; 325380 (Box 19, Folder 337-338)
    - Grape Receipts, 1922; 325379 (Box 19, Folder 339-341)
    - Grape Receipts, 1922-1923; 325378 (Box 20, Folder 342)
    - Grape Receipts / Certificates of Weight and Measure, 1923; 325377 (Box 20, Folder 343)
    - Grape Receipts, 1924; 325376 (Box 20, Folder 344)
    - Grape Receipts and Related Material, 1925; 325375 (Box 20, Folder 345)
    - Grape Receipts, 1926; 325374 (Box 20, Folder 346)
  - Expense Records, 325370
    - Expenses, 1911-1913; 325372 (Box 21, Folder 347)
    - Statements and Receipts, 1912-1923; 1933; 325371 (Box 21, Folder 348-364)
  - Accounts Payable and Receivable, 1919-1923; 325369 (Box 21, Folder 365)
- Labor Records, 1915-1933; 4; 325360; 0.83 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
  This series consists of daily time reports, statements, and time books for day laborers, many of Japanese descent, who worked picking grapes for the George F. Johnston Company.
  Related material can be found filed under the name of individuals in.
  - Daily Time Reports, 1915-1923; 325367 (Box 22, Folder 366-375)
  - Daily Time Reports, 1923-1927; 325366 (Box 23, Folder 376-378)
  - Statements for Japanese Labor, 1916; 325365 (Box 23, Folder 379)
  - Picking Labor, 1917-1921; 325364 (Box 23, Folder 380)
  - Time Books, 1919-1920; 325363 (Box 23, Folder 381)
  - Monthly Time Book, 1929-1940; 325362 (Box 23, Folder 382)
  - Picking Labor, 1932-1933; 325361 (Box 23, Folder 383-384)
- Bank Records, 1911-1950; 5; 325343; 11.42 Linear Feet (12 boxes)
  This series consists of returned checks, deposit slips, and statements, as well as checkbooks and promissary notes relating to the banking activities of the George F. Johnston Company.
  Files are arranged by type.
  - Checkbooks, 1912-1914; 325359 (Box 24, Folder 385-388)
  - Promissary Notes and Related Material, 1917-1929; 325358 (Box 24, Folder 389-391)
  - Deposit Slips, 1911-1923; 325357 (Box 24, Folder 392-403)
  - Deposit Slips, 1924-1932; 325356 (Box 25, Folder 404-413)
  - Statements, 1917-1925; 325355 (Box 25, Folder 414-419)
  - Statements, 1926-1927; 325354 (Box 26, Folder 420-421)
  - Statements, 1934; 325353
  - Checks, 1926; 325352 (Box 26, Folder 422)
  - Checks, 1912-1916; 325351 (Box 27, Folder 423-426)
  - Checks, 1917-1920; 325350 (Box 28, Folder 427-430)
  - Checks, 1920-1922; 325349 (Box 29, Folder 431-434)
  - Checks, 1922-1925; 325348 (Box 30, Folder 435-438)
  - Checks, 1925-1928; 325347 (Box 31, Folder 439-442)
  - Checks, 1928-1930; 325346 (Box 32, Folder 443-446)
  - Checks, 1930-1932; 325345 (Box 33, Folder 447-450)
  - Checks, 1932-1950; 325344 (Box 34, Folder 451-453)
- Oversize, 325336; 5.36 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
  - Ledger (from Series II), 325342 (Box 35, Folder 454)
  - Ledger (from Series II), 325341 (Box 36, Folder 455)
  - Ledger (from Series II), 325340 (Box 37, Folder 456)
  - Shipping Log (from Series II), 325339 (Box 38, Folder 457)
  - Form, Car Manifest (from Series II), 325338 (Box 38, Folder 458)
  - Statements (from Series V), 325337 (Box 38, Folder 459)